<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: writing | Will Roe&#146;s blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/blog/categories/writing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-26T17:38:10+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Will Roe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NaNoWriMo begins]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/2010/11/05/nanowrimo-begins.html"/>
    <updated>2010-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/2010/11/05/nanowrimo-begins</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve started to write my book for <a href="http://www.nanowrimo.org/eng/user/541245" title="My NaNoWriMo profile">NaNoWriMo</a>. For those who don&#8217;t know, the goal is to write a novel (or, more accurately, a first draft of a novel) in a month - November. A novel, in this competition is defined as a work of fiction totaling 50,000 words. It sounds like a lot for a month initially. Then you break that down to 1,667 words per day - which sounds manageable - I tried writing a chapter last month and got 2,033 words done in about an hour and a half.</p>

<p>Day 1 of November proceeded in the same way every day had for the last couple of weeks. Suffice to say I have been rather overloaded at work and have had to put in a lot of hours - usually till about half past midnight to get things done. This is not a good recipe for becoming a best selling author. Day 1, therefore, ended with a word count of zero. Having committed myself to this challenge, I felt the failure keenly.</p>

<p>Day 2 of November showed no signs of being any different. This time, however, I was determined to get writing, whatever happened. I left work as soon as I could, squeezed myself onto the overcrowded train to Clapham Junction and popped into Debenhams to pick up my repaired watches. Even though I was eager to get home and get typing, I was in Debenhams so I decided to have a wander around the mens department. Masterful procrastination I know! I must have been there for around half an hour - bought two jumpers, a white shirt and two ties. Debenhams is a dangerous place. Then I finally made my merry way homewards. The rest of the evening involved trying to write while fielding various questions and requests from colleagues on Skype. I don&#8217;t recommend this as a strategy for writing or even as a strategy for working. It&#8217;s definitely not a good combination for one&#8217;s sanity. However, I managed a measly 500 words. I was too embarrassed to update my word count on my profile though and went to sleep feeling defeated.</p>

<p>Day 3 might as well be forgotten entirely. Quite apart from the work I continued to do during the evening, I made no attempt to write anything - content to investigate various programming ideas and generally waste my time watching programmes on the iPlayer&#8230;until quite late actually - for no good reason. Novel? What novel?</p>

<p>Today was different. Well, not so much actually. By the time work was over, I was pretty much exhausted. I elbowed, pushed and shoved my way onto the inhumane device some people laughably refer to as public transport and made my way home like a zombie with a mission. Slow but determined. I only hope I have more literally skill than your average zombie. Or failing that, raw typing speed.</p>

<p>So aside from the work I inevitably had to do this evening, I&#8217;ve completed 1,788 words, bringing my total so far to 2,288. I am obviously well short of where I should be but I&#8217;m hoping I can put some serious typing hours in on the weekend. It&#8217;s not like I&#8217;ll have anything else to do. Except procrastinate of course.</p>

<p>If anybody else out there in the ether is having problems writing their novel, or writing anything for that matter, rest assured your problems are not unusual. I&#8217;m still wavering between determination to complete the challenge to get my first novel written; and defeat, apathy that no matter how hard I try, life will always get in my way. When I was at school, if a teacher had set me homework to write a 2,000 word essay or story, I would have left it to the last minute, written less than half of what was required and handed it in late. If I don&#8217;t rise above this pattern of under-achievement now, I fear I never will. So, in summary, I will finish this novel on time. I might not enjoy it, but I will complete it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
