<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: books | Will Roe&#146;s blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/"/>
  <updated>2016-08-16T23:04:34+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Will Roe]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[2014 in books]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/2015/01/06/2014-in-books.html"/>
    <updated>2015-01-06T14:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.wjlr.org.uk/2015/01/06/2014-in-books</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>According to <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/">GoodReads</a> I read 17 books
this year. Here are some I really liked.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><img src="https://d.gr-assets.com/books/1394357588l/19932464.jpg" class="book-cover">
<h2>
  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19932464-kindred">Kindred by Octavia Butler</a>
</h2>
</p>

<p>Kindred is classified as sci-fi, but that doesn’t do it justice
really. It’s more of a sci-fi conceit (time-shifting) to allow Butler
to immerse the reader in the world of 1815 on a plantation with
slaves. The protagonist is black and the abrupt time shift lands her
in palpable danger. The relationships between characters was always
nuanced and interesting and the tension was high throughout - tension
from real danger. I especially appreciated the subtle way Butler
weaved in historical names and events into the narrative. I will
definitely be reading more of Octavia Butler’s books.</p>

<p><img src="https://d.gr-assets.com/books/1383652605l/18754367.jpg" class="book-cover">
<h2>
  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/18754367-nothing-o-clock">Nothing O&#8217;Clock by Neil Gaiman</a>
</h2>
</p>

<p>Part of a series of short stories, one for each Doctor, released on
the 50th anniversary of Doctor Who. This was an undemanding
entertaining read and I intend to read more of them.</p>

<p><img src="https://d.gr-assets.com/books/1328327063l/13127093.jpg" class="book-cover">
<h2>
  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13127093-flat-earth-news">Flat-Earth News by Nick Davies</a>
</h2>
</p>

<p>We all know the media are dreadful, but just how dreadful and why?
This book attempts to shine some light on the shady world of British
media (although for the most part the same problems exist elsewhere).
It is somewhat unscrupulous in aiming its critical eye at broadsheet
and tabloid alike and generally castigates broadsheets for pumping out
unchecked nonsense because we expect them to be a cut above the
tabloids (spoiler: they’re not). Shocking, sickening, depressing
- exactly what you’d expect from a book about newspapers.</p>

<p><img src="https://d.gr-assets.com/books/1407785478l/22903174.jpg" class="book-cover">
<h2>
  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22903174-clipping-through">Clipping Through by Leigh Alexander</a>
</h2>
</p>

<p>This book by my favourite games journalist - Leigh Alexander - takes
you into the surreal world of games journalism itself. Part stream of
consciousness and part short biography this is a world most of us have
no idea about. It kept me entertained on a few train commutes.
<a href="https://gumroad.com/l/aisCU">You can and should buy it here</a></p>

<p><img src="https://d.gr-assets.com/books/1401632138l/22387085.jpg" class="book-cover">
<h2>
  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22387085-a-natural-history-of-dragons-a-memoir-of-lady-trent">A Natural History of Dragons by Marie Brennan</a>
</h2>
</p>

<p>The first part of a series of books about the main character - Lady
Trent. A cross between Pride and Prejudice and Reign of Fire, sort of.
Thoroughly entertaining and I shall be reading the rest of the series.</p>

<p><img src="https://d.gr-assets.com/books/1328302275l/10081041.jpg" class="book-cover">
<h2>
  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/10081041-the-long-ships">The Long ships by Frans Bengtsson</a>
</h2>
</p>

<p>This Swedish classic about Vikings in the 10th century in Denmark was
a surprisingly good read. The humour was super dry and for some
considerable time it passed me by. My main criticism of it is that
it’s rather overly long and the novelty of the sarcasm wore out well
before the end for me.</p>

<p><img src="https://d.gr-assets.com/books/1351039314l/11272152.jpg" class="book-cover">
<h2>
  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/11272152-jane-eyre">Jane Eyre by Charlotte Brontë</a>
</h2>
</p>

<p>Quite simply a must read. I particularly enjoyed cross-referencing
with King Lear and the various other literary works Brontë weaves in.</p>

<p><img src="https://d.gr-assets.com/books/1348918036l/2639853.jpg" class="book-cover">
<h2>
  <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/2639853-to-boulez-and-beyond">To Boulez and Beyond by Joan Peyser</a>
</h2>
</p>

<p>The first half of this book is a biography of composers from Debussy
to Boulez, roughly speaking. Lots of time is spent covering
Schoenberg, Berg and Webern as you might expect. The second half of
the book is a biography of Boulez himself. I found the combination
fascinating since it put the musical trends and works of Boulez in
perspective wonderfully. This book lead me to seek out and appreciate
a number of compositions which makes it my favourite of the books I
read in 2014.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
